Guide to the Eric McKitrick papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Eric McKitrick Papers,
1934-2001.
McKitrick, Eric L.
21.42 linear feet (51 manuscript boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5420132
Eric. L McKitrick, a historian of American History, was a professor at Columbia University from 1960-1989. He is known for his work on the development of the party system, slavery and the Old South, and Andrew Johnson and Reconstruction (1960). His papers include teaching materials and files, correspondence, and extensive research files related to The Age of Federalism: The Early American Republic, 1788-1800 (1993). There is also documentation of his activities with Grace Church, the Century Association, and the Historical Society of the Episcopal Church.
Biographical Note
Born on July 5, 1919, in Battle Creek, Michigan, Eric L. McKitrick graduated from Flint Central High School in 1937, and attended Flint Junior College (1937-1939) and Hillsdale College (1940-1941). He served in the United States Army from 1941-1945, and spent time stationed in New York City. In 1947, he enrolled in the Columbia University School of General Studies. He received a Bachelor's degree in 1949, and subsequently received two degrees in history from Columbia University; a Master's degree in 1951 and a Ph.D. in 1959. He was also a Columbia University Fellow (1951-1952) and taught as a Lecturer in American History in the School of General Studies (1952-1954).
McKitrick taught at the University of Chicago (1955-1959) and Douglass College at Rutgers University (1959-1960) before joining the history department faculty at Columbia University in 1960. McKitrick became a full professor in 1965 and a professor emeritus upon his retirement in 1989. During his career, McKitrick also held visiting professorships at Vassar College, Smith College, Cambridge University, and Oxford University.
Much of McKitrick's research focused on the development of the American party system and slavery and the Old South. His best-known work is Andrew Johnson and Reconstruction (1960). In this book, McKitrick argued that Johnson was at fault for the failures of his policies, a position that challenged the prevailing theory that these failures were caused by Republican Radicals. The book received the American History Association's John H. Dunning Prize. It was reissued in 1988, and remains an important work in the historiography of the Reconstruction. He also co-authored The Age of Federalism: The Early American Republic, 1788-1800 1993) with Stanley M. Elkins of Smith College. The book represented the culmination of over twenty-five years of research work. It received the Bancroft Prize in 1994 and the Cox Book Prize from the Society of the Cincinnati in 1995.
Outside of his professional career, McKitrick devoted many years of service to Grace Church and served on many of its committees. He was also involved in the Century Association and the Historical Society of the Episcopal Church.
McKitrick married Edyth Carol Stevenson of Flint, Michigan on December 26, 1946. The couple had two sons and two daughters. McKitrick died on April 24, 2002 in New York City.
Scope and Content
The papers document McKitrick's teaching activities, professional activities and relationships, and research work on The Age of Federalism: The Early American Republic, 1788-1800 (1993). There is also material related to McKitrick's activities with Grace Church, the Century Association, and the Historical Society of the Episcopal Church.
The papers include comprehensive coverage of McKitrick's teaching activities. He kept files for all of his lectureships and professional appointments (1952-1990). These files include general teaching files for particular course topics and chronological files for individual classes that he taught at several institutions. His teaching files include syllabi, reading lists, and extensive lecture outlines. His files on individual classes include class-specific syllabi, examination questions, notes, and correspondence with students and teaching assistants. McKitrick kept files on teaching assignments for masters and doctoral seminars, and on individual students, doctoral candidates, and orals and defenses. These files, as well as the alphabetical correspondence files, document not only McKitrick's teaching activities but also his working relationships with graduate students pursuing academic research work.
The papers are rich in professional correspondence. McKitrick's correspondents include many prominent historians, including Eric Foner, Richard Hofstadter, Mike Wallace, and C. Vann Woodward. There is extensive correspondence with Stanley Elkins, with whom he co-wrote several articles and The Age of Federalism. The papers also include correspondence with many of his current and former students and dissertation advisees. The correspondence documents McKitrick's relationships within the scholarly community and also shows, together with his book reviews, his thoughts on other historical research projects.
The papers do not comprehensively document all of McKitrick's research activities. There are personal business files that relate to many of his articles and book reviews; these files contain correspondence, notes, and drafts. There are extensive research files available only for The Age of Federalism. These files include correspondence with co-author Stanley Elkins, communications with research assistants, drafts, and notes. McKitrick also kept fan letters, reviews, and files on a related symposium and prizes received for the book.
There is also some documentation of McKitrick's professional activities outside of Columbia University, but it is not extensive in scope. McKitrick served on the Executive Board of the Society of American Historians for many years, and was also involved in the University Seminars held at Columbia University. There are records related to both of these activities. There is also documentation of his work on consulting projects, grant submissions and projects, evaluation teams, advisory committees, and award committees. Also included are files related to speeches, lectures, and comments and presentations related to specific conferences.
There is little personal material in the papers, although there is some documentation of McKitrick's activities outside of his professional career. McKitrick kept correspondence received from his friends, parents, and future wife during World War II. There is also material related to McKitrick's membership and activities in Grace Church, the Historical Society of the Episcopal Church, and the Century Association. McKitrick also kept a small amount of juvenilia, student material, and a file on his father's singing career with the Flint Civic Opera.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series.
Series I: Personal Files and Activities, 1944-2001
Subseries I.1: Personal Files, 1944-2001
Subseries I.2: Personal Activities, 1964-2001
Series II: Columbia University, 1952-1999
Subseries II.1: General Files, 1952-1999
Subseries II.2: History Department, 1961-1990
Subseries II.3: Teaching Activities, 1952-1990
Series III: Teaching Activities Outside of Columbia University, 1955-2000
Subseries III.1: Personal Business and Other Material, 1955-2000
Subseries III.2: Courses, 1955-1980
Series IV: Professional and Research Activities, 1947-2001
Subseries IV.1: Organizations, Seminars, and Projects, 1951-2001
Subseries IV.2: Writing Projects, 1950-2001
Subseries IV.3: Andrew Johnson and Reconstruction, 1950s-1960, 1989-1990
Subseries IV.4: The Age of Federalism: The Early American Republic, 1788-1800, 1967-1998
Subseries IV.5: Speeches and Lectures, 1950s-1995
Subseries IV.6: Publications, 1947-1999
Series V: Correspondence, 1937-2001
Subseries V.1: Professional, 1940s-2001
Subseries V.2: Alphabetical File, 1953-2000
Subseries V.3: Personal and Family Correspondence, 1937-1946
Series VI: Student Material and Juvenilia, 1934-1953
Subseries VI.1: Juvenilia, 1934-1944
Subseries VI.2: Student Material, 1940-1953
Subjects
Columbia University.--Dept. of History--Faculty.; Grace Church (New York, N.Y.); Elkins, Stanley M.--Correspondence.; McKitrick, Eric L.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975--Correspondence.; Woodward, C. Vann (Comer Vann), 1908-1999--Correspondence.; United States--Politics and government--1789-1809.; United States--History--Constitutional period, 1789-1809.; United States--History--Outlines, syllabi, etc.; United States--History--Study and teaching (Higher); Historians--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions..
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Gift of Edyth McKitrick, 2005.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Personal Files and Activities
  This series contains biographical material and files related to McKitrick's family, personal business, and activities outside of his professional career.
  - Subseries I.1: Personal Files, 1944-2001
    consists of curriculum vitae, headshot photographs, and a few files on personal business. It includes a file on the singing career of McKitrick's father, Fred McKitrick, with the Flint Civic Opera.
    - Pictures (of me), Undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Alumni--Flint Central, Flint J.C., Hillsdale, Columbia G.S., circa 1949-1987 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Vita, circa 1968, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      (This includes information on Stanley Elkins and the project that became The Age of Federalism)
    - Flint Civic Opera, 1944-1951, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Invitations, circa 1969-1973 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Extra-C., 1992-2001 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Cottage File, 2000-2001 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.2: Personal Activities, 1964-2001
    documents McKitrick's activities with the Century Association, Grace Church, and the Historical Society of the Episcopal Church.
    - Century Club
      (The Century Association)
      - 1973-2001, (5 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 3 to 7)
      - Committee on Literature, 1997-2001 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Grace Church
      - 1964-1999, (2 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 9 to 10)
      - Music Committee
        - 1965 (Box 12, Folder 11)
        - 1966-1992, (5 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Calling Committee, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Nominating Committee for Vestry, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Worship Committee, 1992-1996, (4 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 8 to 11)
      - Grace Church School, 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Grace Church School History, 1994-1995 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Canon Law, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Church Club, 1968, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 15)
        (Church Club of New York)
      - Janet Kraft, Grace Church, 2000, Undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - St. John's Church (Sand Point, Michigan), 1998 (Box 13, Folder 17)
        (Includes photographs)
      - Organ Study, 1993-1994 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Organ Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Patrick Allen: New Organ Search, 2000-2001 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Historical Society of the Episcopal Church
      - 1992-2001, (9 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 4 to 12)
      - Words and Worship
        - Lent, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 13)
        - Revised, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Series II: Columbia University, 1952-1999
  Material related to McKitrick's professional career at Columbia University comprises this series. The teaching material relates both to his work as a lecturer (1952-1954) and as a faculty member of the History Department (1960-1990) at the University
  - Subseries II.1: General Files, 1952-1999
    is made up of personal business files on personnel matters and material related to general events, occasions, and University committees.
    - General Studies (G.S.) U.S. History Survey--Columbia, 1952-1954 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Columbia-Informal-Colleagues-Miscellaneous, Etc., 1976-1985, 1999 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Retirements-Deaths-Occasions (Columbia), 1989-1999 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Personal University Business--Salary, Leave, Etc., 1960-1989 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Columbia Centennial Committee 1880-1980, 1978-1979 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Committee Business, 1961-1965 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Subseries II.2: History Department, 1961-1990
    consists of McKitrick's files on "department business" and committee work related to the History Department. The committee files include documentation of McKitrick's work on the Curriculum, Executive, and Master's Program committees. McKitrick's chronological files on department business include announcements, correspondence, memoranda, and notes on dissertation defenses.
    - Curriculum Committee, 1961-1962, 1972-1973, (2 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Department Business
      - 1982-1990, (7 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 5 to 11)
      - 1968-1982, (13 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 1 to 13)
      - 1960-1971, (11 Folders) (Box 44, Folder 1 to 11)
    - MA Committee, 1964 (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - Placement, 1972-1973 (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Secretary's Minutes, 1964-1967 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      (Related to the Executive Committee)
    - Commencement, 1961-1996 (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - American History Area Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II.3: Teaching Activities, 1952-1990
    includes course material, chronological files on individual classes, and files on McKitrick's activities with graduate seminars, students, orals and defenses. McKitrick kept files of general course material by course title; these files include syllabi, detailed lecture outlines, and examination questions. He also kept chronological files on individual classes that he taught in the history department. These files include class-specific examination questions, reading lists, syllabi, and correspondence with individual students and teaching assistants. Some of these files, particularly the oldest files, also have additional notes written by McKitrick.
    McKitrick kept separate files related to his teaching of the masters and doctoral seminars and on individual graduate students, doctoral candidates, and orals and defenses. These files include course material, student research proposals, notes, and correspondence. There is additional correspondence with dissertation advisees filed in the Alphabetical File of Series V: Correspondence.
    - Masters Seminar
      - 1960-1973, (10 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 1 to 10)
      - 1974-1985, (9 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 1 to 9)
      - 1985-1990, (5 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Masters Students
      - Inherited-Adopted-Miscellaneous, 1989, Undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
      - Student List, 1960-1990 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Doctoral Seminar
      - 1960-1962, (5 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 8 to 12)
      - 1963-1970, (6 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 1 to 6)
    - Individual Doctoral Candidates, 1960-1970
      - A-E, (2 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 7 to 8)
      - G-Z, (2 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Doctoral Candidates Lists, 1960-1970, 1990 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Individual Students, 1960s, 1980s, (2 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Patronage-Job Market, 1960s (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Orals & Defenses--A-Z, 1960-1990, (7 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 6 to 12)
    - Chronological Files on Individual Classes
      - American History Survey Course, 1984-1989, (5 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 1 to 5)
      - Undergraduate Seminar--Jeffersonian America, 1985-1989, (4 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 6 to 9)
      - Lecture Course--Age of Federalism and Jeffersonian Era, 1974-1984, (16 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 10 to 25)
      - Lecture Course--Civil War and Reconstruction, 1969 Spring and 1973 Spring (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - Colloquium--Jeffersonian American, 1972 Fall (Box 41, Folder 2)
      - Lecture Course--Middle Period, 1968 Fall and 1972 Fall (Box 41, Folder 3)
      - Colloquium--Federalist Era, 1971 Fall (Box 41, Folder 4)
      - Colloquium--Jeffersonian American, 1970 Spring (Box 41, Folder 5)
      - Colloquium--Federalist Era, 1969 Fall (Box 41, Folder 6)
      - Lecture Course--Civil War and Reconstruction, 1967 Spring (Box 41, Folder 7)
      - Lecture Course--Middle Period, 1966 Fall (Box 41, Folder 8)
      - Colloquium--Jeffersonian America, 1965 Fall (Box 41, Folder 9)
      - Lecture Course--Civil War and Reconstruction, 1964 Summer Session (Box 41, Folder 10)
      - Colloquium--Jacksonian America, 1964 Spring, 1965 Spring, 1966 Spring (Box 41, Folder 11)
      - Colloquium--Jeffersonian American, 1964 Fall (Box 41, Folder 12)
      - Colloquium--Jeffersonian American, 1963 Fall (Box 41, Folder 13)
      - Lecture Course--Civil War and Reconstruction, 1961 Spring, 1962 Spring (Box 41, Folder 14)
      - Lecture Course--Middle Period, 1960 Fall, 1961 Fall (Box 41, Folder 15)
      - Colloquium--Literature of American History (McCaughey-Graff-Garraty), 1984-1986 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Teaching Materials
      - American History Survey Course 1492-1877, 1984 Fall-1989 (Box 45, Folder 5 to 6)
      - The Age of Federalism 1787-1801 (History W4637x), circa 1980 (Box 45, Folder 7)
      - The Age of Federalism 1787-1801, 1974 (Box 45, Folder 8)
        (Revised 1983-1984)
      - The Jeffersonian Era 1801-1828, 1975 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Political and Social History of the United States 1828-1860 (History G6675x--Formerly History 177), Undated (Box 46, Folder 2)
      - Political and Social History of the United States 1828-1860 (History G6675x--Revised), circa 1966 (Box 46, Folder 3)
      - Political History of the United States 1860-1877 (Columbia University G6676y & Vassar College 385a), 1967-1968 (Box 46, Folder 4)
      - G.S. Survey Course--Lecture Outlines, 1952-1954 (Box 46, Folder 5)
        (American History course taught by Elkins & McKitrick)
- Series III: Teaching Activities Outside of Columbia University, 1955-2000
  This series includes personal business files and teaching material on positions and visiting professorships that McKitrick held outside of Columbia University.
  - Subseries III.1: Personal Business Files, 1955-2000
    documents personal business issues and activities related to McKitrick's appointments and visiting professorships, and include information on the appointments, housing, departmental meetings, social and speaking engagements, and invitations. There is some general information related to courses taught during these appointments filed with this material.
    - Cambridge, 1973-1974
      - Pitt Professorship (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Academic-Professional (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Cambridge Classes (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Social Life, Etc. (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Speaking Invitations England, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Oxford, 1979-1980
      - Harmsworth Professorship Oxford (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Oxford Faculty of Modern History (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Oxford Classes, Lectures, and Seminars (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Queen's College Oxford (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - England Speaking Invitations (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Social and Miscellaneous (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - University of Chicago, 1955-1959
      - Evaluations of Student Papers, 1956, Undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Appointment, Salary, University College, Etc., 1954-1959 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Students--Veysey-Kelley et al., 1958-1964 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Course Syllabi, Undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Smith College Seminar, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Douglass - Rutgers, 1959-1960
      - Miscellaneous/Business, 1958-1960, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Grades-Courses-Miscellaneous (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Vassar, 1968-1970 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Smith College
      - On Leave, 1967-1968 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Ziskind Lectures, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Smith-Northampton, 1970s-2000, (2 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 12 to 13)
        (Some of this material is related to summer research trips)
  - Subseries III.2: Courses, 1955-1980
    includes teaching material for individual classes taught at the University of Chicago, Douglass College at Rutgers University, Vassar College, Cambridge University, and Oxford University. The files include detailed lecture outlines, examination questions, and syllabi.
    - University of Chicago & Douglass College/Rutgers, circa 1955-1960
      - Growth of American Civilization Part I (Box 46, Folder 6)
        (1492-1840 and 1492-1865, respectively)
      - Growth of American Civilization Part III (Box 46, Folder 7)
        (1898-1941 and 1865-1941, respectively)
    - University of Chicago, circa 1955-1959
      - Techniques of Argument in Theoretical Writing (Box 46, Folder 8)
      - Problems in American History 1828-1860 (History 373C) (Box 46, Folder 9)
      - Post-Civil War America 1865-1900 (History 373D) (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - Douglass College/Rutgers--Development of Western Civilization (History 101-102), 1959-1960 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - Vassar College--Political History of the United States 1860-1877 (Columbia University G6676y & Vassar College 385a), 1967-1968 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Cambridge University, 1973-1974
      - The Era of Federalism: Politics and National Identity 1787-1801 (Box 47, Folder 2)
      - The Civil War and Reconstruction (Box 47, Folder 3)
      - Untitled (Box 47, Folder 4)
        (Lecture notes for American History 1492-1877)
    - Oxford University, 1979-1980
      - The Early American Republic 1787-1809 plus Harmsworth Inaugural Lecture (Box 47, Folder 5)
      - American Nationalism and the Jacksonian Era 1812-1844 (Box 47, Folder 6)
- Subseries IV: Professional and Research Activities, 1947-2001
  This series contains files on activities related to professional organizations and research, writing, and other projects outside of Columbia University.
  - Subseries IV.1: Organizations, Seminars, and Projects, 1951-2001
    includes material related to McKitrick's work in professional associations, seminars, consulting, and research projects. The files include information on his work on grant submissions and projects, evaluation teams for academic programs, advisory committees, and award committees. The files also contain comments on exhibits and projects in his area of expertise, including the Jefferson Papers project. The material includes correspondence, memoranda, notes, proposals, reports, and other materials.
    - Society of American Historians, 1969-2001, (3 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 7 to 9)
    - University Seminar on Early American History, 1991-1996 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - University Seminar in American Civilization, 1964-1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Institute for Advanced Studies, 1970-1971, 1976-1977, (2 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 3 to 4)
      (Princeton University)
    - New-York Historical Society--Betsy McC., J. Bell, and others, 1980-1987 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - John Jay College, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      (NEH Curriculum Program Advisory Committee)
    - West Point United States Military Academy (USMA), 1969-1977 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      (Evaluation Team of the Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools)
    - Yale Conference on Local History, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - University of Virginia Honors Meeting, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      (McKitrick served as an external examiner for the History Honors Program)
    - American History Lab Project, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Tufts Seminar, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Jefferson Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      (Response to a request for comments on the Jefferson Papers Project)
    - Madison Papers & allied matters, 1970-1973, 1984, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Hamlin Papers-Ames Papers & Miscellaneous Library Business, 1960-1965 (Box 18, Folder 5)